I am an education researcher with over ten years of experience in project coordination and supervision, as well as data management, analysis, and reporting. I am happiest working at the intersection of K-12 education research and data management planning, helping researchers and practitioners strategize and implement reproducible workflows and organization-wide data management practices that lead to more secure, reliable, and reproducible data. Ultimately, my goal is to allow researchers to spend more time using data to make positive changes in the field, and less time wrangling their data into a usable and shareable format.

Technical Skills

R, Qualtrics, Git and GitHub, SPSS, Microsoft Access, Stata, Quick Base, SQL, SharePoint, Tableau

Education

University of Minnesota

Minneapolis, MN

MASTER OF PUBLIC POLICY

2009-2011

• Concentration: Advanced Policy Analysis

University of Missouri

Columbia, MO

BACHELOR OF SOCIAL WORK

2001-2005

· Concentration: Research Methods

Experience

Freelance Remote

DATA MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

Mar 2022 - Present

- · Providing research data management consulting, training, and data wrangling services to improve organizational workflows.
- Composing a draft of the book 'Data Management in Large-Scale Education Research' at https://datamgmtinedresearch.com

Streamline Data Science Remote

Data Scientist Nov 2021 - Mar 2022

- Created example client facing crm dashboard in R flexdashboard to demonstrate services.
- Built Google Trends R flexdashboard to show capabilities of automatic updating data.

Missouri Prevention Science Institute

University of Missouri

DIRECTOR OF DATA STRATEGY

May 2019 - Nov 2021

- Strategized data management plans for over ten actively funded projects and oversaw their implementation.
- Created standard operating procedures for all data management systems and provided annual staff training on systems.
- Built a team SharePoint site and oversaw migration of all files from our former system to the new site.
- Merged, cleaned, manipulated, queried, and documented data collected from school districts, state education agencies, surveys, assessments, and observations using R.

DIRECTOR OF RESEARCH IMPLEMENTATION

Jul 2016-May 2019

- Supervised project staff, ensuring successful completion of data collection activities for six federally funded randomized controlled trial studies and two county funded projects.
- Delivered quarterly trainings to staff on data collection methods.
- Designed and built data collection tools including Qualtrics surveys and Access tracking databases.
- Build reports, dashboards, and visualizations for the dissemination of data.

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE Aug 2013 - Jul 2016

- Coordinated activities for two Institute of Education Sciences funded randomized controlled trial studies.
- Collected data in schools through classroom observations, surveys, and assessments.
- Established trusting relationships with school district partners.

Big Brothers Big Sisters of Eastern Missouri

St. Louis, MO

EVALUATION AND OUTCOMES MANAGER

Jun 2011 - Aug 2013

 Oversaw the collection, analysis, and dissemination of data relating to performance management, outcomes, and stakeholder satisfaction.

May 2023

Center for Advanced Studies in Child Welfare

University of Minnesota

RESEARCH ASSISTANT Jan 2010 - Jul 2011

• Evaluated the effectiveness of the Hennepin County Attorney's Office truancy intervention program using qualitative and quantitative methods.

Humphrey School of Public Affairs

University of Minnesota

Teaching Assistant Aug 2010 - Dec 2010

• Taught lab sessions of a graduate level introductory statistics course using Stata.

Hennepin-University Partnership

University of Minnesota

GRADUATE ASSISTANT Sep 2009 - May 2010

• Connected County officials with University faculty to develop effective partnerships to improve the community.

Service

POWER Issues in Data Management in Education Research Hub

Remote

Organizer Jan 2022 - Present

• Organize and host monthly meetups and presentations on data management topics

R-Ladies St. Louis St. Louis, MO

CO-ORGANIZER Aug 2020 - Present

• Organize and host monthly workshops on programming in R

Center for Open Science Unconference on Open Scholarship Practices in Education

Remote

ADVISORY COMMITTEE MEMBER Oct 2022 - Mar 2023

• Assist in planning the 2023 event

RStudio ConferenceWashington D.C.

Teaching Assistant July 2022

• Teaching Assistant for What They Forgot to Teach You About R Workshop

LaunchCode St. Louis, MO

Teaching Assistant Jan 2018 - July 2018

• Developed curriculum and taught data analysis once a week for a cohort of 25 women looking to make a career transition.

AmeriCorps St. Louis Education Team

St. Louis, MO

TEAM LEAD Aug 2007 - Aug 2008

• Tutored elementary students, led educational programming, and supervised a team of three tutors

Oversaw Data Management for the Following Grants

Boone County Children Services Fund: The FACE of Boone County, PI: Aaron Thompson, (2020-2024)

Institute of Education Sciences: Enhancing the Capacity of Rural Schools to Identify, Prevent, and Intervene in Youth Mental Health Concerns: The National Center for Rural School Mental Health, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2019-2024) (R305C190014)

Institute of Education Sciences: Efficacy study of Discipline in the Secondary Classroom, PI: Carl Sumi, (2018-2023) (R305A170040)

National Institute of Justice: Evaluation of a principal training program to promote safe & civil schools, PI: Keith Herman, (2017-2021) (2016-CK-BX-0004)

Institute of Education Sciences: Evaluation of a training program to promote effective school leadership, PI: Keith Herman, (2017-2022) (R305A170180)

Institute of Education Sciences: Implementing a comprehensive data-based coordinated System of care for school districts to promote youth academic success and social emotional development: A researcher-practitioner partnership, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2017-2019)

Institute of Education Sciences: Evaluation of a self-monitoring training program for elementary school students, PI: Aaron Thompson, (2015-2019) (R305A150517)

Boone County Children's Services Fund: Boone County Mental Health Coalition County-wide Initiative to Support

May 2023 2

School-age Youth, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2014-2020).

Institute of Education Sciences: The Classroom Check-Up: Supporting teachers in classroom management using a web-based coaching system, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2013–2018) (R305A130375)

Institute of Education Sciences: Evaluation of a classroom management training program for middle school teachers, PI: Keith Herman, (2013–2018) (R305A130143)

Institute of Education Sciences: Evaluation of a Video-based Modeling Program to Promote Effective Teacher Classroom Management Practices, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2010-2015) (R305A100342)

Publications

Cohen, D., Lewis, C.G., Eddy, C.L., Henry, L., Hodgson, C. & Huang, F.L. (2021) In-School and Out-of-School Suspension: Behavioral and Psychological Outcomes in a Predominately Black Sample of Middle School Students. School Psychology Review, DOI: 10.1080/2372966X.2020.1856628

Henry, L., Reinke, W.M., Herman, K.C., Thompson, A.M. & Lewis, C.G. (2020) Motivational interviewing with at-risk students (MARS) mentoring: Addressing the unique mental health needs of students in alternative school placements, School Psychology Review, 50:1, 62-74.

Huang, F., Lewis, C., Cohen, D., Prewett, S., & Herman, K. (2018). Bullying involvement, teacher-student relationships, and psychosocial outcomes. School Psychology Quarterly, 33(2), 223-234.

Lewis, C.G., Herman, K.C., Huang, F.L., Stormont, M., Grossman, C., Eddy, C., & Reinke, W.M. (2017). The utility of single-item readiness screeners in middle school. Journal of School Psychology. 64, 1–16.

Presentations

Lewis, C. (2023). Cleaning Medical Data in R. A forthcoming workshop for the R in Medicine conference June 5-9, 2023, Online.

Lewis, C. (2022). Data Management Workflow for Education Research Studies. Guest lecture given to a graduate research methods class at the University of Houston-Clear Lake, Online.

Lewis, C. (2022). 10 Common Data Management Mistakes. Presented for the Society for the Study of School Psychology, Early Career Foundation, Online.

Lewis, C. (2022). A Comparison of Packages to Generate Codebooks in R. A lightning talk for R-Ladies NYC, Online.

Lewis, C. (2021). Data Management in Large-Scale Education Research. Series of workshops given for Missouri Prevention Science Institute, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO.

Lewis, C. (2019). Cleaning Messy Data in R. Presented at R-Ladies St. Louis Meetup, Washington University in St. Louis.

Lewis, C. (2019). Introduction to R. Guest lecture for LaunchCode CoderGirl Data Analysis track, St. Louis, MO.

Lewis, C. (2018). Survey Says: You can use Tableau to Impact School Climate. Presented at Tableau Fringe Festival APAC, Online.

May 2023 3